ORIGINAL STORY BY NATSU HYUUGA
（原作：日向夏）
THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、組織名均為虛構）
MOREOVER, THE STORY HAS NO RELATION TO REAL-LIFE INCIDENTS AND EVENTS.
（與任何特定事件或現象無關）
She has no understanding of chastity.
她簡直是毫無貞操
She's a picky eater too!
她也很挑嘴
It's not like she'd die.
又不會死
-So cold! -The warming stones help a little, but…
-好冷 -暖石幫了小忙，但是…
To have nothing to do in this cold is torture.
在這寒風當中 無事可做也真是種折磨呢
The wind is so chilly!
風好冷啊
At least have some sort of tent…
至少給我們帳篷吧…
This seating is made to foster hostility among the four concubines.
這樣的座位安排 像是在煽動四位嬪妃間的敵意
Look. That lady is the Empress Dowager.
妳看，那位就是皇太后
She's very youthful.
還真是年輕呢
She's quite young, actually.
實際上也真的很年輕
Because she gave birth to the Lord at…
因為她生下皇上的時候才…
She must've worked hard to give birth to him!
還真是努力啊
The Empress Dowager has two children,
皇太后有兩個孩子
the Lord and his younger brother.
皇上和他的弟弟
But it's rumored that
但謠傳
the brother is very ill and can't leave the house often.
弟弟非常體弱多病，不太露面的樣子
It seems like he was here until recently, but…
剛剛他似乎還有來這裡，但是…
I see.
是喔
What? You call this plain?
什麼？妳竟然說土氣？
An attendant is to serve her master.
侍女就該盡心侍奉自己的主子
What's the point of dressing up?
做那麼多沒用的打扮是有何居心？
Did you hear that?
妳聽到了嗎？
It's the master who suffers
如果侍女的外表糟糕
when her attendant looks poor.
辛苦的可是主子呢
I'm so pissed!
氣死我了！
Those attendants are Lady Lihua's…
那些人是梨花娘娘的侍女…
Oh no, Yinghua's at it. They started a battle by proxy.
不妙，櫻花真是的 又開始代替娘娘出征了
Let's go, Maomao.
我們也走吧
She even hired that ugly duckling, that's to be expected.
她都雇用了那個醜女 這樣也是理所當然的吧
Ugly duckling? Is she talking about me?
醜女？在說我嗎？
That is so embarrassing!
長那樣子，真是丟人現眼
What did you say?
妳說什麼？
-Yinghua! -Calm down!
-櫻花 -冷靜
They haven't realized?
她沒發現嗎？
We were so close at the Crystal Pavilion!
明明在水晶宮時還對她那麼親切
If you get too carried away, I'll tell Father!
妳如果再囂張，我就去向我父親告狀
Then I'll make sure you physically can't tell on anyone.
那我就把妳的身體弄到無法告狀吧
Huh?
咦？
It was just a courtesan joke…
那只是個妓女式的玩笑而已
Apologize to Maomao!
快跟貓貓道歉
Why are you suddenly all quiet?
怎樣？怎麼突然靜下來了？
I'll leave you alone for now!
我就先饒了妳們
-Huh? -You…
-什麼？ -妳…
You better be grateful!
感謝我吧！
What's up with them?
她們是怎麼回事？
Hey, are you okay, Maomao?
貓貓，妳沒事吧？
They don't know you're really this cute.
明明就這麼可愛
It doesn't bother me.
我不在意
Do you want to switch warming stones?
比起那個，要換暖石嗎？
Not only did she suffer misfortune,
她不僅命途多舛
she even mistrusts men so much that she dirties her face…
對男人的高度戒心 甚至不惜弄髒自己的臉
She desperately suffered horrible bullying
她在水晶宮被人百般欺凌
at the Crystal Pavilion for two months…
拼死拼活忍耐了兩個月
She didn't complain once,
從來沒抱怨過一句話
and she doesn't want to worry us…
還這麼為我們著想
It makes sense that the kind-hearted Sir Jinshi watches out for her!
心地善良的壬氏大人特別關照她 也是合情合理
They're making up stories again.
又在妄想些什麼了
Doesn't she even know her position?
她搞不清楚自己的立場嗎？
Look at that red clothing!
看看那一身的紅！
Another battle by proxy.
那邊也在代替娘娘出征啊
It's the Virtuous versus the Pure.
是德妃和淑妃的侍女
Those two groups don't get along well, either.
那兩方人馬也是互看不順眼呢
The Virtuous Concubine is very young at 14,
德妃年僅十四歲，非常年輕
while the Pure Concubine is a veteran at 35.
而年高德劭的淑妃已經三十五歲
Of course they don't get along!
也難怪會合不來囉
And, they were formerly mother and daughter-in-law.
更何況她們原本還是婆媳
Mother and daughter-in-law?
婆媳？
So… This is a bit complicated,
這有點複雜…
but the two Ladies were originally the former Emperor's concubine
兩位娘娘原本一位是先帝的嬪妃
and the current Lord's concubine.
而另一位是現在皇帝的嬪妃
But then, the former Emperor passed away.
但後來先帝駕崩了
The former Emperor's concubine became a monk,
先帝的嬪妃一度出家為尼
then came back as the current Emperor's concubine.
還俗之後 又以皇帝嬪妃的身分回到宮中
The former Emperor passed away five years ago.
先帝在五年前駕崩
Concubine Ah-Duo, who was a Lady at the time, was 30-years-old.
那時的阿多妃是三十歲
The Virtuous Concubine, Lishu, was nine at the time.
德妃里樹妃才九歲
I know it's politics, but to be married at nine…
我知道這是政治聯姻 但在九歲就成婚…
Can you believe it? A nine-year-old mother-in-law.
難以置信吧？九歲的婆婆什麼的
A nine-year-old mother-in-law…
九歲的婆婆…
A mother-in-law?
婆婆？
So…
那麼…
The one who was concubine to the former Emperor was…
先帝之前的嬪妃是…
Lady Lishu?
里樹娘娘？
So that is the young mother-in-law?
那位就是年幼的婆婆？
I think you've noticed,
雖然我覺得妳看到就明白了
but the Virtuous Concubine, Lady Lishu, is still quite young.
不過德妃里樹娘娘還是很幼小呢
It seems like it.
是啊
Traditionally, the Virtuous Concubine should be wearing white.
原本德妃應該要穿白色的服裝
But that dark pink color…
但那身深桃紅色…
It clearly overlaps with Lady Gyokuyou, The Precious Concubine.
顯然和貴妃玉葉娘娘的服飾撞上了
Maybe she doesn't notice things like that.
看來是個不會看場合的孩子呢
The warming stones were a big help. Please make them again.
暖石真的幫了大忙，要再麻煩妳了
Yes, ma'am.
好的
So cold…
好冷
If you're cold, you should have these.
如果會冷，這些就拿去用吧
Here.
拿吧
You're too nice.
妳人也太好了
Asking whether you can share with the attendants in the Crystal Pavilion.
竟然把暖石分給水晶宮的侍女
You even asked for permission from Lady Gyokuyou.
還請求了玉葉娘娘的許可
It's nothing.
沒什麼啦
A hair clip?
髮簪？
That's how they recruit talented people hidden in the flower garden.
他們就是像那樣做 來勸誘隱藏在花園裡的優秀人才
I see.
是喔
It can have other meanings though.
也有不同的意思就是了
I said, it can have other meanings!
我就說還有不同的意思嘛！
Meanings, huh?
不同的意思啊
This is for you, miss.
請收下吧，小姑娘
I guess he's giving them out to everyone
他是不想讓侍女覺得受辱
so that no attendants are embarrassed.
所以把髮簪分給大家嗎？
Thanks.
謝謝
I'm Lihaku.
我是李白
Nice to meet you!
請多指教
He's like a big dog.
好像一隻大狗
Woof, woof!
汪汪
You got that? Show me.
妳收到髮簪了？快讓我看看
It's a participation prize.
這是參加獎
That's not enough, don't you think?
就那一件，不覺得太少嗎？
Long time no see.
好久不見
Long time no see, My Lady.
好久不見了，娘娘
That's all for now.
就這樣，沒別的事
Lady Lihua?
梨花娘娘？
Let's go. Goodbye, all.
走吧，保重
Lady Gyokuyou…
這下子玉葉娘娘…
Might get a little more than upset.
可能不會只是鬧彆扭而已
What are you going to do?
這麼多髮簪，怎麼辦？
Wow.
哇
This is quite impressive.
這樣看起來還真是壯觀
He must be more higher-up than I imagined.
他的官位比我想像的還高
He fits right in with all the soldiers.
混在一群武將當中也絲毫沒有違和感
That soldier from before is there too.
剛剛的那名武將也在
He's in the last seat. He's young, so he might have been promoted.
雖然排在最後 但他很年輕，也算是年少有成吧？
That glittery eunuch isn't here.
那位光采奪目的宦官不在呢
But that doesn't matter.
算了，無所謂
Now, time for poison testing!
試毒的時間到了
No cloudiness to the contact areas.
接觸到的部分顏色並未變深
No strange scents, either.
也沒有奇怪的氣味
But a poison tester's job isn't over until she swallows…
但把食物吞下肚也是試毒人的工作
Now rinse my mouth with fresh water…
接著用清水漱口…
A poison tester's life is expendable.
試毒人的性命可是無足輕重呢
I'm the only one who tastes poison for fun.
以試毒為樂的人大概只有我了吧
If possible, I'd love some puffer fish!
反正都要試毒，要是有河豚就好了
Sneaking its organs into soup….
將牠的內臟巧妙地摻到湯裡…
The way it tingles my tongue is irresistible!
那舌尖的麻痺感真是讓人無法抗拒
Concentrate!
專心
Raw fish and vegetables. The Emperor's favorite.
這道生魚拌蔬菜，是皇上的最愛
It was served at the rear palace sometimes.
有時候後宮也會奉上這道菜
It usually contains blue fish,
平常都是使用鯖魚
but today it's jellyfish.
但今天是海蜇皮
The Food Service in charge of the Emperor's meals
負責替皇上準備膳食的御膳房
would never mistake his favorite ingredient.
絕不會搞錯他最愛的食材
Lady Gyokuyou doesn't have any foods she can't eat.
玉葉娘娘沒有不吃的東西
They must've messed up the food distribution.
配膳一定是出錯了
She doesn't like fish?
她不喜歡吃魚嗎？
I guess she can't leave anything uneaten in front of the Emperor.
在皇上的面前，也不得不吃光吧
I wish I hadn't seen that.
看到討厭的東西了
Did you see, Lihaku?
李白，你看到了嗎？
That poison tester looks determined.
有個試毒人看起來很有氣魄呢
What's so fun about watching people eat
看著別人一邊害怕一邊吃東西
while fearing for their lives?
到底有什麼樂趣？
Just look!
快看啦
That poison tester…
那名試毒人…
It's the girl from before.
是剛剛那個小姑娘
How delicious is it?
到底有多好吃？
This is poison.
這有毒
-Poison in the Precious Concubine's soup? -Is it really poisonous?
-貴妃的湯裡有毒？ -真的有毒嗎？
The poison tester drank it!
試毒人喝下去了吧
Minister! What are you…?
大臣，您做什麼…
Formal wear is so uncomfortable…
正式服裝也太不舒服了吧…
The Minister drank the soup and collapsed!
大臣喝了湯昏倒了
Apothecary…
藥師…
Apothecary!
藥師
How do you do, Sir Jinshi?
壬氏大人，您好嗎？
You're in a great mood.
好的是妳吧？
Oh no, I was excited by the poison. It's like I smiled at him!
不妙，陶醉在中毒的感覺中 結果看起來像在笑一樣
Where are you taking me?
您要做什麼？
To the medical room.
帶妳去醫局
I spit out the poison. There's nothing wrong with my body.
我把毒吐掉了，身體不會有事的
I actually wanted to swallow it right there.
其實本來想就這樣把毒吞下去的
If I had, the poison would be circulating all around me…
那樣子的話 現在毒性就會在我身體各處發作…
Sir Jinshi, um…
壬氏大人…
What is it?
怎麼了？
Please give me the leftover soup!
請把剩下的湯給我
You're stupid, aren't you?
妳是笨蛋嗎？
I'm ambitious, you mean.
請說我很有上進心
After you left,
妳離開之後
someone doubted that it was poison, drank it, and collapsed.
有人懷疑湯裡沒毒 結果喝下去之後昏倒了
What idiot did such a thing?
那個蠢蛋是誰？
The Minister. Now, people are panicking even more.
大臣，託他的福現在大家更慌亂了
In that case, use this.
這樣的話，請用這個吧
It's an antiemetic drug. You can vomit so much that your stomach turns around.
這是催吐藥 功效是吐到讓胃整個翻過來
That's a poison on its own.
那才是毒藥吧
Hey!
啊！
A new hair clip?
新的髮簪？
So eunuchs get hair clips too?
所以宦官也會收到髮簪嗎？
Now that I think about it, his collar is disheveled.
說起來，他的衣領有點凌亂
He's not as glittery as usual.
也不如平常光彩奪目
Is this why I didn't see him at the banquet?
難道是因為這樣 我才沒有在宴席上看到他嗎？
But now, he looks like any young man his age…
不過，這樣子與其說 是和年紀相仿的青年
Actually, he looks quite young.
不如說還有幾分像是少年
He looks better this way.
這樣子比較好呢
It works! As expected of medicine from the court doctor!
有用，不愧是尚藥局的藥
Are you all right?
妳還好嗎？
Yes. I'm all finished.
很好，我吐完了
Now, tell me what happened.
那就告訴我發生了什麼事吧
Who put poison in Concubine Gyokuyou's food?
是誰在玉葉娘娘的食物裡下毒？
I have someone I want you to bring about that.
關於這點，我想請您帶一個人過來
Who is it?
誰？
Will you call Lady Lishu for me?
德妃，可否請您帶里樹娘娘過來？
Sir Jinshi. What did you need from me?
壬氏大人，你找我有何貴事？
I apologize for calling you to such an unrefined place.
請您來這麼樸素的地方，真是抱歉
Who we really wanted was that attendant there.
真正想找您的人是這位侍女
The attendant?
侍女？
Excuse me.
失禮了
I knew it.
我就知道
Is it seafood you can't eat?
您不能吃海鮮，對吧？
What is this about?
這是怎麼回事？
There are some who can't eat particular foods.
有些人不能吃某些食物
For me, it's soba noodles.
以我來說，我不能吃蕎麥麵
Even though you eat poison happily?
但妳卻能若無其事地吃毒？
Leave me alone.
別在意那個啦
I've tried hard to eat them.
為了適應吃蕎麥麵，我也努力過
But my throat closes up, and I can't breathe.
但氣管會因此收縮而呼吸困難
Even a little bit gives me a rash.
即使吃一小口，也會讓我起疹子
It's hard to adjust the amount, and recovery is slow.
不只很難調整份量 復原的速度也很慢
That's what "not being able to eat" means.
這就是“不能吃某些食物”的意思
Lady Lishu. Is your stomach all right?
里樹娘娘，您的肚子還好嗎？
I can offer you a laxative.
需要瀉藥的話…
How did you know?
妳怎麼知道？
The meal at the garden party was clearly
園遊會的膳食
prepared by the rear palace.
顯然是後宮這邊準備的
The fish and vegetable dish had different ingredients than usual.
但生魚拌蔬菜這道料理的食材 與以往有所不同
I think there was an error
可能是哪裡出了差錯
and Lady Gyokuyou and Lady Lishu's meals got mixed up.
讓玉葉娘娘和 里樹娘娘的膳食被對調了
I see…
是喔…
Is it mackerel you can't eat?
妳不能吃的東西，是鯖魚吧？
This has nothing to do with being a picky eater.
這跟挑食無關
This time, hives were the only symptom,
雖然這次的症狀只有蕁麻疹
but it could cause difficulty breathing.
但有時可能會引起呼吸困難
If you knew this and served it…
明知會如此，卻還奉上這道料理…
It's the same as poisoning someone.
就跟下毒沒兩樣
You. You're the poison tester, right?
妳是試毒人，對吧？
Yes.
對
I've gathered things to look out for
為了以防萬一
in case of emergencies.
我整理了一些注意事項
Of course, the best bet is to not eat it at all.
當然，能不要吃下這類食物 是最好的了
Please look over this.
請仔細看過
There's nothing hard about it.
並沒有什麼困難的內容
But if you mess up once,
但要是出了一點差錯
even a physician can't resolve the issue.
即使是醫官也可能束手無策
This is a life-or-death problem.
這是攸關生死的問題
Please don't forget that.
請千萬不要忘記
That's enough blackmailing.
威脅就到此為止吧
What is this about?
這是怎麼回事？
I'm of low class. Please refrain from touching me.
我是下等階級的人 請不要隨便用手碰我好嗎？
You're the only one who says such things to me.
會這樣說的只有妳吧
They just don't want you to feel hurt, that's all.
大家只是不想讓您不舒服而已吧
Now, I must report to Lady Gyokuyou…
我現在得向玉葉娘娘稟報此事…
Wait. Why did you have the poison tester be present for that?
等等，妳為什麼 也叫試毒人陪同前來？
What do you mean?
您是指什麼事呢？
Don't play dumb. You said to call her.
別裝傻，是妳說要叫她來的吧
Just so I could inform her of everything.
這樣我才可以告訴她注意事項
So you're saying that the servers simply made a mistake?
所以妳的意思是配膳的人搞錯了？
That's not for a mere attendant to know.
一介侍女可不知道這種事
At least tell me this, all right?
至少回答這個問題吧
The target was the Virtuous Concubine, Concubine Lishu, right?
目標是德妃，也就是里樹妃吧？
If there was no poison in any other plate.
如果其他人的盤子裡沒有毒的話
I see…
這樣啊…
I'm so tired.
好累
Does this have something to do with the wood tablet incident?
這件事與前幾天的木簡意外有關嗎？
There were no burns on that attendant just now.
剛剛那名侍女身上沒有燒傷的痕跡
Who could it be…?
到底是誰？
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集預告）
Next episode, "Homecoming."
下一集，《返鄉》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻譯：歐德慧